{
  "title": "Computer_Organization - Secondary_Storage",
  "duration": 86,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Secondary_Storage",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Consider a disk with the following specifications: rotation speed of 6000 RPM,\naverage seek time of 5 milliseconds, 500 sectors/track, 512-byte sectors.\nA file has content stored in 3000 sectors located randomly on the disk. Assuming\naverage rotational latency, the total time (in seconds, rounded off to 2 decimal\nplaces) to read the entire file from the disk is _______ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "29.5",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422854/gate-cse-2024-set-2-question-43#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Consider a 512 GB hard disk with 32 storage surfaces. There are 4096 sectors per\ntrack and each sector holds 1024 bytes of data. The number of cylinders in the hard\ndisk is ____ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "4096",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422798/gate-cse-2024-set-1-question-44#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>A magnetic disk has 100 cylinders, each with 10 tracks of 10 sectors. If each sector contains 128 bytes, what is the maximum capacity of the disk in kilobytes? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>12,80,000</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1280</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1250</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>1,28,000</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>1250</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/331420/isro2020-46\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>A particular disk unit uses a bit string to record the occupancy or vacancy of its tracks, with 0 denoting vacant and 1 for occupied. A 32-bit segment of this string has hexadecimal value D4FE2003. The percentage of occupied tracks for the corresponding part of the disk, to the nearest percentage is: <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>12</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>25</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>38</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>44</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>44</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/213538/isro2018-50\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>SATA is the abbreviation of <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2017)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Serial Advanced Technology Attachment</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Serial Advanced Technology Architecture</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Serial Advanced Technology Adapter</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Serial Advanced Technology Array</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Serial Advanced Technology Attachment</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/128688/isro2017-46\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Consider a disk pack with 16 surfaces, 128 tracks per surface and 256 sectors per track. 512 bytes of data are stored in a bit serial manner in a sector. The capacity of the disk pack and the number of bits required to specify a particular sector in the disk are respectively: <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2016)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>256  Mbyte, 19 bits</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>256 Mbyte, 28 bits</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>512 Mbyte, 20 bits</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>64 Gbyte, 28 bits</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>256  Mbyte, 19 bits</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1209/gate2007-11-isro2009-36-isro2016-21\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>A hard disk system has the following parameters :<br>Number of tracks =500<br>Number of sectors/track =100<br>Number of bytes /sector =500<br>Time taken by the head to move from one track to adjacent track =1 ms<br>Rotation speed =600 rpm.<br>What is the average time taken for transferring 250 bytes from the disk ? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2015)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>300.5 ms</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>255.5 ms</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>255 ms</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>300 ms</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>300 ms</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3479/gate2007-it-44-isro2015-34\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Six files F1, F2, F3, F4, F5 and F6 have 100, 200, 50, 80, 120, 150 records respectively. In what order should they be stored so as to optimize act. Assume each file is accessed with the same frequency <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2015)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>F3, F4, F1, F5, F6, F2</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>F2, F6, F5, F1, F4, F3</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>F1, F2, F3, F4, F5, F6</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Ordering is immaterial as all files are accessed with the same frequency.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>F3, F4, F1, F5, F6, F2</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/37207/isro2015-13\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Consider a typical disk that rotates at 15000 rotations per minute (RPM) and has a transfer rate of 50x\\(10^{6}\\)  bytes/sec. If the average seek time of the disk is twice the average rotational delay and the controller's transfer time is 10 times the disk transfer time, the average time (in milliseconds) to read or write a 512-byte sector of the disk is ______. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "6.1",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8251/gate2015-2-32#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Consider a disk pack with a seek time of 4 milliseconds and rotational speed of 10000 rotations per minute (RPM). It has 600 sectors per track and each sector can store 512 bytes of data. Consider a file stored in the disk. The file contains 2000 sectors. Assume that every sector access necessitates a seek, and the average rotational latency for accessing each sector is half of the time for one complete rotation. The total time (in milliseconds) needed to read the entire file is ____________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "14020",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8354/gate2015-1-44#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>In case of a DVD, the speed of data transfer is mentioned in multiples of? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>150 KB/s</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1.38 MB/s</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>300 KB/s</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>2.40 MB/s</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>1.38 MB/s</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/44397/isro-2013-51\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Consider a hard disk with 16 recording surfaces (0-15) having 16384 cylinders (0-16383) and each\ncylinder contains 64 sectors (0-63). Data storage capacity in each sector is 512 bytes. Data are\norganized cylinder-wise and the addressing format is (cylinder no., surface no., sector no.). A file\nof size 42797 KB is stored in the disk and the starting disk location of the file is (1200, 9, 40).\nWhat is the cylinder number of the last sector of the file, if it is stored in a contiguous manner? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1281</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1282</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1283</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>1284</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>1284</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1540/gate2013-29#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Which RAID level gives block level striping with double distributed parity? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>RAID 10</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>RAID 2</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>RAID 6</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>RAID 5</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>RAID 6</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/52586/isro2011-46\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>A fast wide SCSI-II disk drive spins at 7200 RPM, has a sector size of 512 bytes, and holds 160 sectors per track. Estimate the sustained transfer rate of this drive <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>576000 Kilobytes / sec</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>9600 Kilobytes / sec</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>4800 Kilobytes / sec</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>19200 Kilobytes / sec</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>9600 Kilobytes / sec</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/52486/isro2011-38\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>An application loads 100 libraries at startup. Loading each library requires exactly\none disk access. The seek time of the disk to a random location is given as 10ms.\nRotational speed of disk is 6000rpm. If all 100 libraries are loaded from random\nlocations on the disk, how long does it take to load all libraries? (The time to\ntransfer data from the disk block once the head has been positioned at the start\nof the block may be neglected) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>0.5s</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1.5s</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1.25s</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>1s</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>1.5s</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2146/gate2011-44#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 16,
          "question": "<p>Consider a disk pack with 16 surfaces, 128 tracks per surface and 256 sectors per track. 512 bytes of data are stores in a bit serial manner in a sector. The capacity of the disk pack and the number of bits required to specify a particular sector in the disk are respectively <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>256 Mbyte, 19 bits</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>256 Mbute, 28 bits</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>512 Mbyte, 20 bits</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>64 Gbyte, 28 bits</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>256 Mbyte, 19 bits</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/48058/isro2009-36\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 17,
          "question": "<p>A hard disk has 63 sectors per track, 10 platters each with 2 recording surfaces\nand 1000 cylinders. The address of a sector is given as a triple (c,h,s), where c is the cylinder number, h is the surface number and s is the sector number. Thus, the \\(0^{th}\\) sector is addressed as (0,0,0), the \\(1^{st}\\) sector as (0,0,1), and so on <br><br>The address of the \\(1039^{th}\\) sector is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>(0,15,31)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>(0,16,30)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>(0,16,31)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>(0,17,31)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>(0,16,31)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/43477/gate2009-52#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 18,
          "question": "<p>A hard disk has 63 sectors per track, 10 platters each with 2 recording surfaces\nand 1000 cylinders. The address of a sector is given as a triple (c,h,s), where c is the cylinder number, h is the surface number and s is the sector number. Thus, the \\(0^{th}\\) sector is addressed as (0,0,0), the \\(1^{st}\\) sector as (0,0,1), and so on <br><br> The address (400, 16, 29) corresponds to sector number: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>505035</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>505036</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>505037</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>505038</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>505037</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1337/gate2009-51#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 19,
          "question": "<p>The total time to prepare a disk drive mechanism for a block of data to be read from it is <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>seek time</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>latency</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>latency plus seek time</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>transmission time</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>latency plus seek time</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/17263/isro2008-49\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 20,
          "question": "<p>Raid configurations of the disks are used to provide <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Fault-tolerance</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>High speed</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>High data density</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>(A) &amp; (B)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>(A) &amp; (B)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1496/gate1999-2-18-isro2008-46\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 21,
          "question": "<p>For a magnetic disk with concentric circular tracks, the seek latency is not linearly\nproportional to the seek distance due to <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>non-uniform distribution of requests</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>arm starting and stopping inertia</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>higher capacity of tracks on the periphery of the platter</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>use of unfair arm scheduling policies</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>arm starting and stopping inertia</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/443/gate2008-32#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 22,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following RAID level provides the highest Data Transfer Rate (Read/Write) <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>RAID 1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>RAID 3</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>RAID 4</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>RAID 5</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>RAID 1</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/49539/isro2007-56\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 23,
          "question": "<p>A hard disk system has the following parameters :<br>Number of tracks = 500<br>\nNumber of sectors/track = 100<br>\nNumber of bytes /sector = 500<br>\nTime taken by the head to move from one track to adjacent track = 1 ms<br>\nRotation speed = 600 rpm.<br>\nWhat is the average time taken for transferring 250 bytes from the disk ? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>300.5  ms</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>255.5  ms</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>255 ms</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>300  ms</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>300  ms</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3479/gate2007-it-44-isro2015-34\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 24,
          "question": "<p>Consider a disk pack with 16 surfaces, 128 tracks per surface and 256 sectors per track. 512 bytes of data are stored in a bit serial manner in a sector. The capacity of the disk pack and the number of bits required to specify a particular sector in the disk are respectively: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>256 Mbyte, 19 bits</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>256 Mbyte, 28 bits</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>512 Mbyte, 20 bits</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>64 Gbyte, 28 bits</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>256 Mbyte, 19 bits</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1209/gate2007-11#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 25,
          "question": "<p>A disk has 8 equidistant tracks. The diameters of the innermost and outermost tracks are 1 cm and 8 cm respectively. The innermost track has a storage capacity of 10 MB.<br>If the disk has 20 sectors per track and is currently at the end of the \\(5^{th}\\) sector of the inner-most track and the head can move at a speed of 10 meters/sec and it is rotating at constant angular velocity of 6000 RPM, how much time will it take to read 1 MB contiguous data starting from the sector 4 of the outer-most track? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>13.5 ms</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>10  ms</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>9.5 ms</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>20 ms</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>10  ms</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3846/gate2005-it-81-b\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 26,
          "question": "<p>A disk has 8 equidistant tracks. The diameters of the innermost and outermost tracks are 1 cm and 8 cm respectively. The innermost track has a storage capacity of 10 MB.<br>\nWhat is the total amount of data that can be stored on the disk if it is used with a drive that rotates it with<br>\nI.Constant Linear Velocity<br>\nII.Constant Angular Velocity?<br> <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(I. 80 \\ \\text{MB}; \\;  II. 2040 \\ \\text{MB}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(I. 2040 \\ \\text{MB}; \\;  II 80 \\ \\text{MB}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(I. 80 \\ \\text{MB}; \\; II. 360 \\ \\text{MB}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(I. 360 \\ \\text{MB};  \\; II. 80 \\ \\text{MB}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(I. 360 \\ \\text{MB};  \\; II. 80 \\ \\text{MB}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3845/gate2005-it-81-a\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 27,
          "question": "<p>The storage area of a disk has the innermost diameter of 10 cm and outermost diameter of 20 cm. The maximum storage density of the disk is 1400 bits/cm. The disk rotates at a speed of 4200 RPM. The main memory of a computer has 64-bit word length and 1\\(\\mu s\\) cycle time. If cycle stealing is used for data transfer from the disk, the percentage of memory cycles stolen for transferring one word is <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2004)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>0.50%</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1%</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>5%</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>10%</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>5%</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3694/gate2004-it-51\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 28,
          "question": "<p>Using a larger block size in a fixed block size file system leads to <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2003)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>better disk throughput but poorer disk space utilization</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>better disk throughput and better disk space utilization</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>poorer disk throughput but better disk space utilization</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>poorer disk throughput and poorer disk space utilization</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>better disk throughput but poorer disk space utilization</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/915/gate2003-25#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 29,
          "question": "<p>Raid configurations of the disks are used to provide <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1999)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Fault-tolerance</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>High speed</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>High data density</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>(A) &amp; (B)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>(A) &amp; (B)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1496/gate1999-2-18-isro2008-46\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 30,
          "question": "<p>Formatting for a floppy disk refers to <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1998)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>arranging the data on the disk in contiguous fashion</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>writing the directory</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>erasing the system data</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>writing identification information on all tracks and sectors</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>writing identification information on all tracks and sectors</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1681/gate1998-2-9\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 31,
          "question": "<p>The data transfer rate of a double-density floppy disk system is about: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1987)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>5K bits/sec</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>50K bits/sec</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>500K bits/sec</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>5000K bits/sec</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>500K bits/sec</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/80281/gate1987-1-x\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}